Okay. בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
It's good to be back.
Welcome to
הוריות. Horayot. דף י'. Daf Yud. Daf 10.
We are in the third chapter and we're kind of in the
middle of the narrow lines on דף י' עמוד א' Daf Yud
Amud Aleph in the משנה Mishnah that's in the middle. Thank you
for Rabbi Meisner for pulling a little bit ahead. We're continuing to
look at the difference between the כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach and the
נשיא, Nasi, but ahead of us, just ahead of us, are a
couple of fascinating stories and then some interesting commentary on
certain פסוקים Pesukim in regards to the נשיא Nasi specifically
to the מלך. Melech. Okay. The משנה Mishnah tells
us: חטאו עד שלא נתמנו. Chatu ad shelo nitmanu. So who are
we talking about? We're talking about the כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach and
the נשיא Nasi and the King.
And
the משנה Mishnah is saying what is the situation what if they
sinned, they had a made a transgression that if they did purposefully
its punishment would be כרת Karet and if they did erroneously the
punishment is חטאת Chata'at or the consequence is חטאת? Chata'at? But they
did that before they were appointed to their positions, before they were
either כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach or נשיא. Nasi. ואחר כך נתמנו, Veachar
kach nitmanu, and then they were
appointed, הרי אלו כהדיוטות. harei elu kehedyotot. They are like regular people
and they would bring the sacrifice of a regular person.
רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon Omer: אם נודע להם עד שלא נתמנו
חייבין, Im noda lahem ad shelo nitmanu chayavin, ומשנתמנו פטורין. umishenitmanu peturin.
If they know, what Rabbi Shimon is saying is for a transgression
we need an act, we need a חטא, chet, and we also
need the awareness of the חטא, chet, we need the knowledge.
If that happens
before they were appointed, then they are liable, but if it happens
after, then they are completely exempt.
There's something, and the whole discussion is about when the status takes
effect and how long does the status last? We saw in the
previous משנה Mishnah and the גמרא Gemara discussion that
the
כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach from the moment he becomes כהן משיח Kohen
Mashiach going forward, he remains in this status and for the, even
if he doesn't act in his status he remains in it, and
for the נשיא Nasi only when he is for the נשיא Nasi
who as we'll see in a minute is a מלך, Melech, only
while he is
in
his job. Okay. איזהו
נשיא? Ezehu Nasi? Asks the משנה Mishnah to
define. זה מלך Zeh Melech שנאמר: shene'emar: מכל מצוות השם אלוהיו Mikol
mitzvot Hashem elohav שאין על גביו אלא השם אלוהיו. she'ein al gabav
ela Hashem elohav. So we have a פסוק Pasuk in ויקרא פרק
ד' Vayikra Perek Dalet the verse 22.
Okay.
That the משנה Mishnah is asking you who is this נשיא Nasi
that we're talking about? It's a King. Why? Because we have a
פסוק Pasuk that says
like from all the מצוות Mitzvot of השם Hashem his God and
the
משנה Mishnah understands it to mean that there is no one above
him except his God. Therefore he is the highest. I marked the
תנ"ך Tanakh if you want.
And there's a few other references that we need later. That there's
no one above him except השם Hashem his God and this is
going to be important in
just a few minutes. Okay. The גמרא Gemara is asking about the
beginning of this משנה, Mishnah, about this חטאו עד שלא נתמנו. Chatu
ad shelo nitmanu. מנא הני מילי? Mena hani mili? Where do we
know this from? דתנו רבנן Detanu Rabanan in ויקרא Vayikra chapter 4,
Leviticus chapter 4, verse 3: אם הכהן המשיח יחטא. Im HaKohen HaMashiach
yecheta. Literally if the anointed priest will
sin. And then it
says: פרט לכהן... Prat lekohen...
It excludes all his transgressions that he did earlier before being a
כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach and if he transgressed then he'll bring a
regular
sacrifice. והלא דין הוא. Ve-halo din hu. We could, why do we
need a פסוק? pasuk? We could just understand it like,
this is like it could be a קל וחומר kal va-chomer from
our learning about the נשיא Nasi
about the כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach and
נשיא. Nasi. ומה נשיא שמביא בשגגת מעשה, U-mah Nasi she-mevi bi-shgagat ma'aseh,
so to speak, בלבד, bilvad, right? The נשיא Nasi only brings the
offering for his שגגה shgaga ואין מביא על הקודמות ve-ein mevi al
ha-kodmot and he doesn't bring anything for the previous transgression.
משיח שאין מביא אלא על העלם דבר עם שגגת מעשה אינו דין
שלא יביא על הקודמות. Mashiach she-ein mevi ela al he-elem davar im
shgagat ma'aseh eino din she-lo yavi al ha-kodmot. It's obvious. The
נשיא Nasi doesn't bring on the קודמות kodmot and קל וחומר kal
va-chomer the משיח Mashiach also, משיח, Mashiach, God, the כהן
משיח Kohen Mashiach should not bring on previous sin transgressions. But the
גמרא Gemara rejects it. No.
אם אמרת בנשיא שכן מביא חטאתו משעבר תאמר במשיח שכן מביא חטאתו
משעבר,
Im amarta be-Nasi she-ken mevi
chatato mi-she-avar tomar be-Mashiach she-ken mevi chatato mi-she-avar, like we can almost,
like we can reverse the קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. We don't know
which direction is it going, right? Is it, do we learn from
the נשיא Nasi a קל וחומר kal va-chomer to the כהן משיח
Kohen Mashiach or from the כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach to the נשיא?
Nasi? And we'll see that we're going a little bit back and
forth
how to learn from one to another. Okay. Hold on. Lost my
space
here from excitement. הואיל, Ho'il, sorry, הואיל ומביא חטאתו משעבר יביא על
הקודמות תלמוד לומר המשיח יחטא חטאת כשהוא משיח מביא כשהוא הדיוט אינו
מביא.
Ho'il u-mevi chatato mi-she-avar yavi al ha-kodmot Talmud lomar ha-Mashiach yecheta
chatat keshe-hu Mashiach mevi keshe-hu hedyot eino mevi. So we understand from
the פסוק pasuk המשיח יחטא ha-Mashiach yecheta that he must be כהן
משיח Kohen Mashiach and anything that happened to him prior to being
כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach doesn't count. ותניא נמי גבי נשיא כהאי גוונא.
Ve-tanya nami gabe Nasi ke-hai gavna. We can understand also the same
for the נשיא. Nasi. אשר נשיא יחטא פרט לקודמות. Asher Nasi yecheta
prat le-kodmot.
We'll see in a minute that there's a little bit of a
play or back and forth about these two פסוקים. psukim. One says
about the כהן Kohen אם im and the משיח Mashiach אשר. asher.
Yes.
When does the כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach know that he's the כהן
משיח? Kohen Mashiach?
He has to be anointed.
No, but I'm saying does he, what period are we talking about?
He couldn't know when they say before he became the כהן Kohen
would he bring his special offering? Is that the question?
He already was a כהן, Kohen, but you know, then he became,
he sinned, but then at some point he's you know you're next
in line but didn't go through the official inauguration process, you know,
that could be like one of those intermediate cases where he could
know before he becomes כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach at some point.
So like at that point then he
would, that was what, that was what רב שמעון Rav Shimon was
saying.
That was, that was רב שמעון'ס Rav Shimon's point, like you know,
if he managed to figure it out somewhere in the intermediate period
then he wouldn't bring it, whereas תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says even
then he wouldn't bring it because the whole thing has to be
once he was the משיח. Mashiach. I mean he'd be a
כהן Kohen from when he was born right but not necessarily the
כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach so there'd be a time when he becomes
responsible like Michael explained. Right.
Okay, got it. Thank you.
משיח
והלא דין הוא ומה משיח שמביא חטאתו משעבר אינו מביא על הקודמות
נשיא שאין מביא חטאתו משעבר אינו דין שלא יביא על הקודמות.
Mashiach ve-halo din hu u-mah Mashiach she-mevi chatato mi-she-avar eino mevi al
ha-kodmot Nasi she-ein mevi chatato mi-she-avar eino din she-lo
yavi al ha-kodmot.
We can go back and forth.
The משיח Mashiach brings his חטאת chatat for things he's done but
not for things before he was anointed. נשיא Nasi doesn't do it,
then
is it not logical that he will also not bring the sin
offering for things that were prior, for the קודמות, kodmot,
which is what we said.
Right. Right. It goes a little bit back and forth. מה למשיח
שכן שכן אין מביא בשגגת מעשה תאמר בנשיא ש...
Mah le-Mashiach she-ken she-ken ein mevi bi-shgagat
ma'aseh tomar be-Nasi she... מה למשיח שכן שכן אין מביא בשגגת מעשה
תאמר בנשיא שמביא בשגגת מעשה.
Ma limeshiach sheken sheken ein
meivi bishigagat maaseh tomar benasi shemeivi bishigagat maaseh.
So the anointed priest, right, he does not bring—what is like special
about him—he does not bring a sin offering for transgressions that he's
done בשגגת מעשה, bishigagat maaseh,
right, then also for the נשיא nasi or for the king brings
an offering for the performance of an like an unwitting performance of
an action even without this this ruling הואיל
ומביא בשגגת מעשה יביא על הקודמות
hoil umeivi
bishigagat maaseh yavi al hakodmot תלמוד
לומר אשר נשיא יחטא talmud lomar asher nasi yecheta שחטא והרי הוא
נשיא ולא שחטא ועודנו הדיוט. shechata vaharei hu nasi velo shechata veodenu
hedyot. Okay. We have two פסוקים psukim that we're going back and
forth on. One says about the כהן kohen
that
אם הכהן יחטא im hakohen yecheta and about the נשיא nasi אשר
נשיא יחטא. asher nasi yecheta. So he has to be a כהן
kohen in the status of כהן משיח kohen mashiach for this to
like matter for this transgression to matter and for the נשיא nasi
also he has to be נשיא nasi and if he is not
a נשיא nasi then his ruling is like a regular person like
a person who we call a הדיוט. hedyot.
Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to look at this פסוק
pasuk and try to unpack additional things. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan אשר
נשיא יחטא יכול גזירה. asher nasi yecheta yakhol gezeirah. So the פסוק
pasuk says how would you translate אשר? asher? I guess that, right.
That or should. I
think that.
I
Or should a... I think that.
I think that.
It's like... okay, let me tell you what the גמרא Gemara is
trying to say. This is different from the אם. im. The כהן
kohen about the כהן kohen it says אם הכהן המשיח יחטא. im
hakohen hamashiach yecheta. If. So if not, then not, right. But for
the נשיא nasi it says אשר. asher. So is that a גזירה?
gezeirah? Like does that mean that the נשיא nasi must transgress? Like
that this is inevitable? For the כהן kohen it can be if
yes or no but for the נשיא nasi does that mean that
you know he must?
Okay. אשר נשיא יחטא יכול גזירה asher nasi yecheta yakhol gezeirah אם
הכהן המשיח יחטא im hakohen hamashiach yecheta תלמוד לומר אם הכהן המשיח
יחטא talmud lomar im hakohen hamashiach yecheta מה להלן לכשיחטא אף כאן
לכשיחטא. ma lehalan liksheyecheta af kan liksheyecheta. So we're learning from both
verses on each other even though they're not identical because of the
similarity of the situation. Because we said about the כהן המשיח kohen
hamashiach about the anointed priest if he will sin then and we
mean when this will happen not that it's a גזירה gezeirah that
it must happen. So we say also about
the
נשיא. nasi. אמר
מר יכול גזירה גזירה מהיכא תיתי?
amar mar
yakhol gezeirah gezeirah meheicha teiti? Like
where else in the תורה Torah do we derive that there can
be a גזירה gezeirah that somebody must sin? Right. If we go
with this פסוק pasuk אשר נשיא יחטא asher nasi yecheta to mean
that the נשיא nasi it's inevitable that he must
sin...
where else do we have an example for such a situation? Ah,
we find an example. אמרי אין אשכחן דכתיב. amrei in ashkechan deichtiv.
We find in Leviticus
14:34 when we talk about the מצורע metzora ונתתי נגע צרעת בבית
ארץ אחוזתכם. venatati nega tzaraat beiveit eretz achuzatchem. I will place צרעת
tzaraat in the homes in the land of where you're where you're
dwelling. Says
בשורה היא להם שנגעים באים עליהם. bsorah hi lahem shenegaim baim aleihem.
Here we have a premonition,
a tidings. Okay. There's some informing, right, בשורה. bsorah. There's some informing
that bad things we presume bad things are going to happen. Now
we know and this is דברי רבי יהודה. divrei rabbi yehuda. We
know the מדרש midrash that says it started out bad and ended
up good because where the צרעת tzaraat struck the homes that meant
that they were you know they'd take them apart and they would
find treasures behind it and all that. But על פניו al panav
initially this is bad. רבי שמעון אומר פרט לנגעי אונסין. rabbi shimon
omer perat lenigaei onsin. So this does not include this case of
the צרעת tzaraat does not include things that are אונסין onsin things
that are beyond one's control.
Look at רש״י. Rashi.
Tell me...
שאם באו נגעים על ידי נפיחת שד, she'im ba'u n'ga'im al y'dei
n'fichat shed, right?
Coming up, coming up about the... what did they mean? I want
to know what they mean
in
the נפיחת שד. nefichat shed.
Like,
the devil did it with נפיחה. neficha. נפיחה Neficha is blowing, like
if a demon blew on it and caused it to become like
נגעים. nega'im.
But it can be a bad blowing.
Whatever, off the record, I don't know what they're really thinking, but
you know.
But they're thinking that there's שדים, shedim, they're thinking that there's some
bad powers, right, that are
blowing
around. Okay.
לאו אמר רבי יהודה בסורא? Lav amar Rabbi Yehuda b'Sura? הכא נמי
אימא גזרה היא הילכך כתיב אם.
Hacha nami eima
gezeira hi hilchach ktiv im. So no, this is
if
this will happen and not that it must happen. We can't assume
that the נשיא nasi necessarily has a גזרה gezeira that he must,
that he
must
transgress. ולרבי שמעון נגעי אונסין מי לא מטמו? U'l'Rabbi Shimon nig'ei onsin
mi lo matmu?
And according to Rabbi Shimon
who talks about the נגעי אונסין, nig'ei onsin, the things that are
beyond one's control that
cause ritual impurity? והתניא, Ve'hatanya, we have a ברייתא braita elsewhere: אדם
כי יהיה, Adam ki yihiyeh, a person shall have, right? The צרעת,
tzaraat, the skin things in the future in Leviticus 13:2. מן הדיבור
ואילך, min hadibur va'eilach, from the time that we got the commandments
and going into the future. The understanding is that before מתן תורה
Matan Torah somebody might have a צרעת tzaraat or might have, we'll
see the זב, zav, but that would not render him impure, like
the category of pure and impure was not relevant before מתן תורה.
Matan Torah.
Okay. והלא דין הוא טימא בזב וטימא בנגעים מה זב מן הדיבור
ואילך אף נגעים מן הדיבור ואילך.
V'halo din hu tima b'zav v'tima b'nega'im mah zav min hadibur
va'eilach af nega'im min hadibur va'eilach. We can make the comparison between
the
זב... zav... translate... no translation... and the נגעים, nega'im, the marks.
And the זב zav is impure from the time the Torah was
given and forward, before that that status had not the same meaning,
and also the נגעים nega'im could be understood to go forward from
then. But this is rejected. אם אמרת בזב שכן אין מטמא באונס
תאמר בנגעים שמטמאין באונס. Im amarta b'zav sheken ein metamei b'ones tomar
b'nega'im shemitam'in b'ones.
If you say that in regards to the זב, zav, he does
not become impure (I've marked the רש"י). Rashi If you say that
in regards to the זב zav he does not become
impure שאין מטמא באונס she'ein metamei b'ones by these circumstances beyond his
control, shall you say that also with the נגעים, nega'im, with the
leprosy marks,
that they impart ritual impurity
that caused because of אונס? ones? So this is our question. Rabbi
Shimon is the question? Yes. Right.
You have the answer.
תלמוד לומר אדם כי יהיה, Talmud lomar Adam ki yihiyeh, as we
just discussed, therefore the Torah says and we bring the פסוק pasuk
of אדם כי יהיה, Adam ki yihiyeh, a person shall be, not
in the present, this is not his status automatically, but he will
be מן הדיבור ואילך. min hadibur va'eilach. And now they're trying to
work out how is it possible that it happens and doesn't happen.
This is what I was curious about the שד. shed. הא אמר
פרט לנגעי רוחות רב פפא אמר פרט לנגעי כשפים.
Ha amar prat l'nig'ei ruchot Rav Papa
amar prat l'nig'ei kshafim. So things that are by spirits or by
sorcery.
Right, so we differentiate between אונס ones and כשפים. kshafim. So when
Rabbi Shimon says that they're not מטמא אונס, metamei ones, he doesn't
mean the אונס ones like before, he means רוחות ruchot and כשפים.
kshafim.
That's our answer for Rabbi Shimon.
That they cause the אונס. ones. No, meaning that would be, you'd
be exempt. Rabbi Shimon says you're not מטמא באונס, metamei b'ones, but
then we had another statement that they are מטמא באונס, metamei b'ones,
so it depends what kind of an אונס, ones, if it's just
an אונס ones on you as a person like, oh you know,
just whatever, it's different than רוחות ruchot and כשפים kshafim which are
not מטמא, metamei, that would be our answer for Rabbi Shimon.
And they're beyond somebody's control.
Okay.
What's the difference between רוחות ruchot and כשפים? kshafim?
רוחות Ruchot are like spirits and כשפים kshafim is like magic.
Done by man... by people... could be, done by people.
רוחות Ruchot is more, okay, supernatural.
It's
like you know, you place a spell on this guy to have
an...
Ghostbusters kind of things. I don't know what that— what they understood—
I would like to know, I don't, you know, I value what
they're saying, but I don't quite understand what they're saying.
Okay. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*: אשר נשיא יחטא asher nasi
yecheta. *Asher Nasi Yechta*. We have a
back to the verse, when this נשיא nasi, *Nasi* or the king
transgresses, this excludes the חולה *Choleh*, פרט לחולה *Prat L'Choleh*.
We'll see in a minute why, so just hold it. Connect to
the recent statement.
Because if he's sick, then he's not the נשיא nasi, *Nasi* at
that time, right?
But what kind of sickness? So like what? If he's sneezing? Not
a cold. Probably like King David was cold, right? So he didn't
count.
Probably means that like, you know, he needs to take a medical
leave of absence.
Well, what's... we just talked about נגעים *Negaim*, right? So this is—
it's gonna go into the צרעת *Tzaraat* and go into some fascinating
stories, I think.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is asking exactly the question
we're asking: משום דהוה ליה חולה איתחלי מנשיאותיה *Mishum Dehavah Leih Choleh
Itchelei Minesiuteih*? What? If somebody like sneezes or has a headache, then
now he stops being the נשיא Nasi *Nasi*? אמר רב אבדימי בר
חמא *Amar Rav Avdimi Bar Chama*: פרט לנשיא שנצטרע *Prat L'Nasi Shenitztera*.
So no, we don't mean somebody sick, we mean somebody stricken with
leprosy. Because the understanding is that leprosy is like
a spiritual illness, right? So that there's something not just that whatever,
he's sneezing, but there's something wrong with his performance or with how
he is. And now they bring us a great story: שנאמר shenemar,
*Shene'emar* מלכים ב *Melachim Bet* in
Kings
2 chapter 15 verse 5: וינגע השם Hashem את המלך ויהי מצורע
עד יום מותו וישב בבית החפשית ויותם בן המלך בן המלך על
הבית *Vayenaga Hashem Et Hamelech Vayehi Metzora Ad Yom Moto Vayeshev Beveit
Hachofshit Veyotam Ben Hamelech Ben Hamelech Al Habayit*. Okay. So this is
the case of עוזיהו Uziyahu *Uzziahu*. He was king of the kingdom
of Judea, and
when
he became a leper, he sat until the day of his death
in what the תנ״ך *Tanach* calls בית החפשית *Beit Hachofshit*. We'll see
that— we want to talk about that. And his son became in—
his son became king on the— on the house, right? על הבית
*Al Habayit*, i.e. on the kingdom.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is asking something interesting and
I need like the— the movie drums preparing for a great story:
מכדי קאמר בבית החפשית מכלל דעד השתא עבד eved הוה *Michdi Ka'amar
Beveit Hachofshit Miklal De'ad Hashta Eved Havah*? Wait, you said about this
king that he was a leper until the day of his death
and so he went to sit
in
the house of the free people.
If you're telling me that now he's going to the house of
the free people, that means that he was a slave until now,
right?
Yes? We're good? Okay. Story.
He was free from the responsibilities of kingship.
Story.
חפשי מן המצוות *Chofshi Min Hamitzvot*.
Yeah, that's what I was thinking but I didn't want to say
that. It's usually what it says, חפשי מן
המצוות *Chofshi Min Hamitzvot*. Yeah, you're thinking of— yeah, you gotta hear
the story.
You gotta hear this story.
You gotta hear this.
כי הא דרבן גמליאל ורבי יהושע הוו אזלי בספינתא *Ki Ha Dirabban
Gamliel V'rabbi Yehoshua Havu Azli Besfinta*. Rabban Gamliel and Rabbi Joshua going
down in boat.
No,
but you'll miss something. You'll see.
You'll see. You can catch up with him tomorrow.
We'll do the next five minutes.
Okay, okay. I have five minutes. Okay, so Rabban Gamliel and Rabbi
Yehoshua going in a boat. בהדי דרבן גמליאל הוה פיתא pita בהדי
דרבי יהושע הוה פיתא pita וסולתא *Behadei Dirabban Gamliel Havah Pita Behadei
Dirabbi Yehoshua Havah Pita V'solta*. Rabban Gamliel travels on this boat with
a פיתא pita *Pita* and Rabbi Yehoshua has פיתא pita *Pita* and
סולתא *Solta* and flour,
fine
flour like cream of wheat. שלים פיתא pita, דרבן גמליאל *Shalim Pita
Dirabban Gamliel*. Rabban Gamliel finished his פיתא *Pita*. סמך אדסולתא דרבי יהושע
*Samach Ad'solta Dirabbi Yehoshua*. He relied on the cream of wheat that
Rabbi Yehoshua brought with him. אמר ליה Amar lei. מי הוה ידעת
דהוה לן עכובא כולי האי דאייתית סולתא *Amar Leih Mi Havah Yad'at
Dehavah Lan Akuva Kulei Hai De'aitit Solta*? Rabban Gamliel says to Rabbi
Yehoshua: How did you know we're going to be so delayed that
you brought סולת solet. *Solet* with you? Now, there is— it's a
משל mashal ונמשל *Mashal V'nimshal* which maybe we don't have time, but
there is one thing that's very cool. אמר ליה *Amar Leih*.
Huh?
The comet, right? Yes.
Right. כוכב אחד לשבעים שנה עולה ומטעה *Kochav Echad Leshiv'im Shanah Oleh
Umateh*. את הספינות או ספנים ואמרתי שמא יעלה ויטעה אותנו. There is
this star that rises every 70 years and
it comes and it confuses the navigation of the
ship leaders, whatever they're called.
Yes, the early source for Halley's Comet.
Yes. So actually if you look it up I was so excited,
he was excited too,
that they knew that there is this
star,
comet, something that rises every 70 years and according to the calculations
of Halley's Comet, you know that too? Supposedly it passed through
in the year 66
and they attribute this
story to that year to Halley's Comet coming by. Cool. Okay רגע.
rega. There is also the משל of what is the ספינה sfina
and what is the 70 years and what is the פיתא and
what is the פיתא and the סולת. solet So the מהרש"א Maharsha
says that this is 70 שנות אדם shnot adam and okay and
so the ספינה sfina they compare this story with the אגדות agadot
of רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana in סנהדרין Sanhedrin
at the end of סנהדרין Sanhedrin and say that the פיתא is
like the bread is the תורה Torah but the פיתא plus the
סולת is תורה Torah and other wisdoms and that they go and
argue against whether it's Jesus or early Christians or whatever other theories
and therefore they go in this boat on this, you know, rickety
ocean where they can lose their way. And רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
has the תורה Torah and that's like solid for him and this
is what he relies on, but רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua brings other
wisdoms, whatever that means, in order to win that argument against—but we
need other wisdom too.
I can't do it now. That's a מהרש"א, Maharsha, yeah. Longer conversation.
Okay.
Thank you, bye. I
was so excited about the comet. Okay, sorry. Okay, so.
He should've called it Rabbi Yehoshua's comet instead of Halley's comet.
Halley is much later, but he's the one that knew of it
first.
Who? Rabbi Yehoshua, right, Rabbi Yehoshua's comet.
They probably call it Halley's comet, but he didn't come around until
17—right.
It's like whatever Lord Coke, right, instead of sandwich.
He was
eating sandwiches long before, long before the Coke. Okay. אמר ליה. רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is extremely impressed, like us.
He's extremely impressed that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is like such a
stargazer, right? And he says to him כל כך בידך ואתה עולה
בספינה? kol kach b'yadcha v'ata oleh basfina? Like wow, you have so
much knowledge and you go you go on the boat? Like do
something with yourself, right?
אמר לו, Amar lo, עד שאתה תמה עלי תמה על שני תלמידים
שיש לך ביבשה. ad she'ata tameh alai tameh al shnei talmidim sheyesh
l'cha bayabasha. Don't spend your time being so impressed with me, but
wonder about those two students that you have on
land: רבי אלעזר חסמא Rabbi Elazar Chisma ורבי יוחנן בן גודגדא v'Rabbi
Yochanan ben Gudgada שיודעים לשער כמה טיפות יש בים
sheyod'im l'shaer kama tipot
yesh bayam ואין להם פת לאכול ולא בגד ללבוש. v'ein lahem pat
leechol v'lo beged lilbosh. You have these two students, Rabbi Elazar Chisma
and Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada, and they can estimate how many drops
are in the ocean and yet they have not a bread to
eat, no פיתא, ולא בגד ללבוש v'lo beged lilbosh and not a
clothing to wear. Wow. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel thought about it and
was very impressed. נתן דעתו להושיבם בראש. natan da'ato l'hoshivam barosh. He's
like, okay, I am going to put them like at the head
of an academy or give them some some great job. Which is
super fascinating because רש"י Rashi says כדי שיהיו מתפרנסים, k'dei sheyihyu mitparnesim,
wherever it is, maybe on the next page,
it's the second
to last רש"י.
Rashi. I marked it from my and my notes. רש"י Rashi says
that so they will be, right, so they will have פרנסה. parnassa.
But the תוספות הרא"ש Tosafot haRosh on the very bottom tiny tiny
print in like the middle of the last wide line says והושיבם
מאי פרנסה איכא? v'hoshivam mai parnassa ika? Like since when since when
is there פרנסה parnassa in the ישיבה yeshiva that he wants to
he wants to put them there? Which is
it's interesting considering conversations today that those conversations are already then. Anyway,
okay.
כשעלה, kshe'ala, when he came from the sea, שלח להם ולא באו,
shalach lahem velo bau, חזר ושלח ובאו. chazar veshalach uvau. So he
sent for
them. I guess they knew why he's calling them, they didn't want
to come, they don't want שררה, serara, they don't want the authority.
חזר ושלח ובאו, chazar veshalach uvau, he sent them again and they
came. אמר להם, amar lahem, remember this whole conversation is connected to
our king עוזיהו who was sent to
בית החופשית, beit ha-chofshit, right? אמר להם, amar lahem, כמדומים אתם ששררה
אני נותן לכם? kimdumim atem she-serara ani noten lachem? You think I'm
giving you שררה serara like I'm giving you some position or something?
We're at the top of יוד עמוד ב. yud amud bet. עבדות
אני נותן לכם. avdut ani noten lachem. I am not giving you
authority like a position to do whatever whatever you want. I'm giving
you a form of slavery. Where do we get this from? שנאמר,
וידברו אליו לאמר אם היום תהיה עבד לעם הזה. vayidabru elav lemor
im hayom tihye eved la-am haze. Okay, this is a fabulous story
and I didn't mark it, and I didn't mark
it, one second.
This story is in the book of Kings I, chapter 12. And
the drama that happens in this
book is that up until then the kingdom was one and now
the kingdom is going to split. And this is the זקנים zekenim
going to speak with רחבעם Rechavam who is the son of שלמה.
Shlomo. And this is what they're, this is their pitch, right? How,
why you want to be king? And they say to him, וידברו
אליו לאמר אם היום תהיה עבד לעם הזה ועבדתם ועניתם ודברת אליהם
דברים טובים והיו לך עבדים כל הימים. vayidabru elav lemor im hayom
tihye eved la-am haze va-avadtam va-anitam ve-dibarta alehem devarim tovim ve-hayu lecha
avadim kol ha-yamim.
The זקנים zekenim tell רחבעם, Rechavam, if today you will be a
servant to this people or a slave, an עבד to these people,
if you worship them and answer them and talk to them good
things, they will be your servants in return.
And as we know, רחבעם Rechavam leaves the advice of the elders
and he says a very, a very famous saying. Am I doing
it right? Huh? Yeah. אבי
יסר אתכם בשוטים ואני איסר אתכם בעקרבים.
avi
yisser
etchem
ba-shotim va-ani ayasser etchem ba-akrabim. My, my father was, you know, whatever,
mildly rough on you and I'm going to be much harder. And
by rejecting, the understanding is by rejecting the position of being the
people's servant, that the kingdom split
and eventually became ישראל ויהודה Yisrael ve-Yehuda and not just the one
kingdom.
So the split, who, who led the split? Somebody who was willing
to serve the people?
No, he did not want that position.
No, he didn't want to.
That's it. He became the next king.
And they revolted? I mean, how did the split occur is what
I'm saying.
That, this is it. Instead of uniting the kingdom and coming together,
right, he wanted his own kingdom in Judea and there was ירובעם
בן נבט Yerovam ben Nevat that took over ישראל. Yisrael.
And the,
I
guess the understanding from here and from the text is that they
become whatever, more selfish kings that
care
about themselves and their worship and ישראל Yisrael becomes more idolatrous and
all that. Okay.
All right. Moving on.
תנו רבנן. אשר נשיא יחטא. asher nasi yecheta, How much more, how
many more things can we get out of these three words in
this
פסוק? pasuk? אמר רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, amar Rabi Yochanan ben Zakai,
אשרי הדור שהנשיא שלו מביא קרבן על שגגתו. ashrei ha-dor she-ha-nasi shelo
mevi korban al shigagato. Rabi Yochanan ben Zakai reads into this פסוק
pasuk אשר נשיא יחטא, asher Nasi yecheta what we said earlier, that
the נשיא, the leader, the king will transgress. He takes the word
אשר, asher, that, and he switches it to אשרי, ashrei, אושר, osher,
happiness. Happy or lucky are the people that their נשיא, that their
king is bringing a קרבן, korban, bringing a sacrifice for the things
that they do wrong because, like, imagine what a great thing. The
king doesn't always, doesn't only bring a sacrifice for things he purposefully
has done wrong, but he brings a sacrifice for like something that
he's done a mistake. If he's like so high,
wow. Okay. אם נשיא שלו מביא קרבן צריך אתה לומר מה הדיוט
ואם על שגגתו מביא קרבן צריך אתה לומר מה זדונו. im nasi
shelo mevi korban tzarich ata lomar ma hedyot ve-im al shigagato mevi
korban tzarich ata lomar ma zedono. He's like, wow, right? This is
amazing. If the king brings a sacrifice,
you're like, oh. Of course the simple people will bring too. And
if the נשיא brings a sacrifice for a mistake, of course he'll
do תשובה teshuvah for things that he does in purpose, right? Isn't
it? Isn't this amazing? Okay. מתקיף לה רבא ברי דרבא אלא מעתה
דכתיב ואת אשר חטא מן הקדש ישלם ובירובעם בן נבט דכתיב ביה
אשר חטא ואשר החטיא הכי נמי דאשרי הדור הוא? Matkif lah Rava
berei deRava ella me'ata dichtiv ve'et asher chata min hakodesh yeshalem u'veYerovam
ben Nevat dichtiv bei asher chata va'asher hecheti hachinamaide ashrei hadoro hu?
He's like, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait. You took this one word,
אשר, asher, and you told me that it's related to אשרי, ashrei,
right? Like אשרי האיש Ashrei ha'ish and
אשרי
יושבי ביתך. Ashrei yoshvei veitecha. So now everywhere where it says אשר,
asher, I am gonna think, happy are those that this happens to
them because of your דרשה drasha here. So what about all these
bad cases? ירובעם בן נבט Yerovam ben Nevat we just mentioned him,
the first king of the separate kingdom of Israel, also says אשר
חטא. asher chata. So is that the same, is that the same
thing? שאני הכא דשני קרא בדיבוריה. Shani hacha deshani kora bediburei. No,
this is exactly why we teach this here because here we have
אשר asher, נשיא יחטא
and we parallel this with the כהן. kohen. This is not a
regular אשר, it's a thing that we can make commentary on. Okay.
דרש רב נחמן בר רב חסדא מאי דכתיב יש הבל אשר נעשה
על הארץ
Darash Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda mai
dichtiv yesh hevel asher na'asa al ha'aretz etc. One second, I have
this פסוק pasuk too. Now we're in קהלת, Kohelet,
Ecclesiastes, chapter 8, verse 14. יש הבל אשר נעשה על הארץ אשר
יש צדיקים אשר מגיע אליהם כמעשה הרשעים ויש רשעים שמגיע אליהם כמעשה
הצדיקים אמרתי שגם זה הבל.
Yesh hevel asher na'asa al ha'aretz asher yesh tzaddikim asher magi'a aleihem
kema'asei haresha'im veyesh resha'im shemagi'a aleihem kema'asei
hatzaddikim amarti shegam zeh hevel. Okay, the whole פסוק, pasuk,
there is,
hold on, let me see,
interesting, the translation says there is a frustration,
I don't know if I would say הבל hevel is frustration, but
okay, that occurs in the world, sometimes an upright man is required
according to the conduct of a scoundrel, right? according to the רשע,
rasha, and sometimes the רשע, rasha, the scoundrel, is required according to
the conduct of the upright, I say all this is frustration. What
do you think about הבל? hevel? I never thought of הבל hevel
as frustration.
More like nothingness or vanity, right? Vanity of vanities, everything is vanity.
Okay, all right, okay. So now continuing the דרשה drasha on this
פסוק. pasuk. אשריהם לצדיקים שמגיע אליהם כמעשה הרשעים של עולם הבא בעולם
הזה אוי להם לרשעים שמגיע אליהם כמעשה הצדיקים של עולם הבא בעולם
הזה.
Ashreihem latzaddikim shemagi'a aleihem kema'asei haresha'im shel olam
haba ba'olam hazeh oy lahem laresha'im shemagi'a aleihem kema'asei hatzaddikim shel olam
haba ba'olam hazeh. Okay.
Happy are the good guys, right? That get things
happen to them in this world according to how the רשעים resha'im
are going to experience the עולם הבא olam haba in the עולם
הזה. olam hazeh. I.e. they suffer in this world. Right? We assume
that how things should be, the צדיקים tzaddikim will enjoy the עולם
הבא olam haba and the רשעים resha'im will suffer in the עולם
הבא. olam haba. So he says, happy אשרי ashrei the צדיקים tzaddikim
that in this
world
suffer like the רשעים resha'im in the עולם הבא olam haba and
woe to the רשעים, resha'im, to the wicked one, to whom happens
in this world according to the experience in the righteous of the,
of the עולם הבא, olam haba, that they enjoy, that they enjoy
this world. Right? It's in theory we want the צדיקים tzaddikim to
be happy and the רשעים resha'im to be suffering, but sometimes that's
not how it goes. The צדיקים tzaddikim get the portion from the
רשעים resha'im in the next world in this world, and vice versa.
Okay,
אמר רבא אטו צדיקי אי אכלי תרי עולמי משני להו?
amar Rava atu
tzaddiki i achlei terei olamei misnei lahu? So is that, is that
to say that if the righteous enjoyed two worlds, it would be
bad for them? Why,
why do they have to suffer in this world? Like, let them,
let them be happy in this world and in the עולם הבא.
olam haba. אלא אמר רבא אשריהם לצדיקים שמגיע אליהם כמעשה הרשעים של
עולם הזה בעולם הזה אוי להם לרשעים שמגיע אליהם כמעשה הצדיקים של
עולם הזה בעולם הזה.
Ella amar Rava ashreihem latzaddikim shemagi'a aleihem kema'asei haresha'im shel olam hazeh
ba'olam hazeh
oy lahem laresha'im shemagi'a aleihem kema'asei hatzaddikim shel olam hazeh ba'olam hazeh.
Rather... That is, the happy are the righteous people to
whom happens in this world according to the experience of the wicked
in this world, i.e., that they enjoy themselves, right, in this world,
and woe to the wicked ones that happens to them in this
world according to the experience of the righteous in this world, like
many righteous people that they that they suffer.
Okay. רב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע אתו לקמיה דרבא. Rav
Pappa veRav Huna berei deRav Yehoshua atu lekamei deRava. So Rav Pappa
and Rav Huna, son of Rav Yehoshua, went in front of Rava.
אמר להם, Amar lahem, אוקימתו מסכת פלן ומסכת פלן, Okimtu masechta pelan
umasechta pelan, did you already study this Masechet and that Masechet?
אמרו
ליה, Amru
lei, אין, In, they said yes. איעתתרתו פורתא, Iatartu purta, did you
get a little bit rich? אמרו ליה, Amru lei, אין דזבנן כטינא
דארעא, In dezavnan ketina deara, we bought a little plot of land.
So they're investing, they're doing well in this world. קרא להו, Kari
lehu, אשריהם לצדיקים שמגיע אליהם כמעשה הרשעים של העולם הזה בעולם הזה.
Ashreihem litzadikim shemagia aleihem kemaaseh hareshaim shel haolam hazeh
baolam hazeh. He said to them, wow,
happy are the righteous people to whom it happens in this world
what happens to the רשעים reshaim in this world. And one of
the commentators, I don't remember who says it, says that the emphasis
here is on the little. When he asks them,
איעתתרתו פורתא, Iatartu purta, not did you get rich, but did you
just get rich a little? And also when they say
דזבנן כטינא דארעא, dezavnan ketina deara, we bought a little plot of
land, we didn't go overboard, because too much wealth is also considered
a danger to
learning
תורה. Torah. The
המאירי, haMeiri,
I have a note that says, says that capturing both תורה Torah
and פרנסה parnassah and wealth in this world is like trying to
hunt for two deers at the same time.
It's a beautiful metaphor because it's so hard to hunt for one
deer.
They fast, they hide, all that. It's hard to hunt for one
deer, but trying to get both תורה Torah and פרנסה parnassah would
be compared to trying to catch two deers in the same time
and how, how hard that would be. אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar Channah amar Rabbi Yochanan,
מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, let's bring another פסוק pasuk from הושע: Hoshea:
כי ישרים דרכי ה' צדיקים ילכו בם ופושעים יכשלו בם.
Ki yesharim darchei Hashem tzadikim
yelchu vam ufoshim yikashlu vam. Right.
This is a great פסוק pasuk and just had an opportunity to
study a whole long thing about this. So
הושע Hoshea says, the path of השם Hashem is
just
or right, straight, but let's say in a more loose translation,
the path of השם is just so. This is just what it
is, right, not good, not bad. But the righteous,
when the righteous walk in it, right, and they continue their journey,
but the פושעים, poshim, the transgressors, when they go in the same
exact path, they fail in it, they stumble in it. What is
that situation? Okay, so there's a great joke, great Jewish joke, that
in the world to come, it's all one big same place.
It's a giant big hall, and משה Moshe is teaching תורה. Torah.
For the good guys, it's heaven. For the bad guys, it's hell.
So it's something like this of trying, and now the גמרא Gemara,
is trying to unpack it and is going to try to find
the situation where the exact same thing can be good for one
and bad for the other. משל לשני בני אדם שצלו פסחיהם אחד
אכלו לשום מצוה ואחד אכלו לשום אכילה גסה זה שאכלו לשום מצוה
צדיקים ילכו בם זה שאכלו לשום אכילה גסה ופושעים יכשלו בם.
Mashal lishnei bnei adam shetzalu pischeihem echad achlo lishum mitzvah ve-echad achlo
lishum achilah gassah zeh
she-achlo lishum mitzvah tzadikim yelchu vam zeh she-achlo lishum achilah gassah ufoshim
yikashlu vam.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to try to refine the
understanding of what does it mean one path that is good for,
same exact path that is good for the good guys and bad
for the bad guys. And as we know from גמרא, Gemara there's
going to be a few examples that we're first going to reject
and then going to refine and come to something that is going
to speak to us more. Okay. The first
one is פסח. Pesach. Right. Okay. Here's two...
excessive eating, right, not for the sake of mitzvah. So one is
a good guy, one is a bad guy. אמר ליה *Amar leih*
ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says to רבה בר בר חנה *Rabbah bar
bar Chana*: רשע קרית ליה *Rasha karit leih*? Like you called it
a wicked? דנהי דלא עביד מצוה מן המובחר *Denehi d'lo avid mitzvah
min hamuvchar*, פסח מיהא קאכיל *Pesach miha kachil*? Like, okay, he didn't
do the mitzvah
in the best way possible, the daintiest way possible, but he still
ate the פסח *Pesach* offering, so that's not like a רשעות *rishut*,
right? He fulfilled the מצוה *mitzvah*. אלא *Ella*, let's try a different
metaphor. אלא משל לשני בני אדם *Ella mashal lishnei bnei adam*, Gemara
goes whatever crazy with its examples, זה אשתו ואחותו עמו בבית וזה
אשתו ואחותו עמו בבית *ze ishto va-achoto imo babayit v'ze ishto va-achoto
imo babayit*. Okay, here's a משל *mashal*, there's this guy, he's at
home with his wife and with his sister. Two people, both of
them are at home with their wife and their sister. אחד נזדמנה
לו אשתו ואחד נזדמנה לו אחותו *Echad nizdamna lo ishto ve-echad nizdamna
lo achoto*. זה שנזדמנה לו אשתו צדיקים ילכו בם וזה שנזדמנה לו
אחותו ופושעים יכשלו בם *ze shenizdamna lo ishto tzaddikim yelchu bam v'ze
shenizdamna lo achoto ufoshim yikashlu bam*. So the one that chanced upon
his wife to have relations with, that's a צדיק *tzaddik*, and the
one that chanced upon his sister, that's a פושע *poshea*. That's the
bad guy. The
Gemara rejects.
Yeah, I mean, what's the implication about the intention there when they
say chanced upon? It means like just happened to them, right? Yeah,
they didn't do it actively.
Doesn't matter, they'll reject it. Like this is not this. Okay, they
say מי דמי *Mi dami*? אנן קאמרינן חדא דרך והכא שתי דרכים
*Anan kaamrinan chada derech vehacha shtei drachim*. Like this is not a
good comparison, forget the intent and all this, this is not a
good comparison because I'm talking to you about one path, right? One
whole Moses teaching Torah. Not two opportunities, a wife and a sister.
Those are two separate things, so that's a choice. It's not the
same thing. Okay, אלא *Ella*, next. משל ללוט ושתי בנותיו *Mashal le-Lot
u-shtei bnotav*. הן שנתכוונו לשם מצוה צדיקים ילכו בם *Hen shenitkavnu leshem
mitzvah tzaddikim yelchu bam*. הוא שנתכוון לשם עבירה Aveira ופושעים יכשלו בם
*Hu shenitkaven leshem aveira ufoshim yikashlu bam*. Okay, let's explore this situation.
How about לוט Lot *Lot* and his daughters?
They, right, they
caused
their father to drink so that they can have offsprings. They thought
that they were the last people in the world and that if
they didn't do it, humanity is doomed and dead, right? So they
intended for the sake of a מצוה *mitzvah*. Here they are the
צדיקים *tzaddikim*, which is fantastic that the Gemara is calling לוט Lot,
*Lot*'s daughters for what they did a צדיקות
*tzidkut*, right, a righteousness. הוא שנתכוון לשם עבירה Aveira. פושע *Hu shenitkaven
leshem aveira poshea*. Now you should push back. We don't have a
lot of time to
do
this, but you should push back and be like, oh, maybe he
also intended a מצוה *mitzvah*. Okay, the Gemara will take us there
and go into all the gory details.
So then it's not... it's not his intention in the story, he's
drunk, right? He's
not a conscious decision, right?
The rabbis will not let him get away with it. Just, you
know, a preview on the next three lines, I'm just telling you.
Okay. He
just exactly asks this: ודילמא הוא נמי לשם מצוה מכוון *V'dilma hu
nami leshem mitzvah mechaven*? Maybe he also intended for the sake of
a מצוה *mitzvah*. Who are you to say? אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*: כל הפסוק הזה לשם עבירה נאמר *Kol hapasuk
hazeh leshem aveira ne-emar*. This whole פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* is for the
sake of transgression.
And we're looking at בראשית Bereishit *Bereishit* chapter... this is oh, בראשית
י"ג
*Bereishit yud gimmel*. Okay, this is great. Again, way beyond the time
here, but
one day, it's very interesting to read לוט Lot *Lot* backwards and
read לוט Lot *Lot* all the way to the beginning of his
relationship with אברהם *Avraham* and see what happened. Like, all of a
sudden we're in chapter 19, right? And it's like the whole city
is on fire and he's escaping and now the scene with the
daughters. What was, I mean, he's אברהם *Avraham*'s nephew. Maybe just things
happened to—where is he? And so רבי יוחנן says the whole פסוק
Pasuk is an עבירה and he's taking us back to בראשית chapter
13. It says וישא לוט
את
עיניו וירא את כל ככר הירדן.
Vayisa Lot et einav
vayar et kol kikar hayarden. I'm playing around with the גמרא Gemara
and I'll tell—you'll see why in a minute—כי כלה משקה. ki kulla
mashke. That is the פסוק Pasuk in chapter 13 in Genesis.
לוט Lot looks up and he sees this whole green land. What's
wrong? רבי יוחנן says this פסוק pasuk is already all עבירה. וישא
לוט, Vayisa Lot, why? Because it's a גזירה שוה gezeira shava with
תישא, tissa, lifted his eyes, ותשא אשת אדניו את עיניה, vatisa eshet
adonav et eineha,
the wife of פוטיפר Potiphar lifted her eyes to see יוסף, Yosef,
right? She desired him. את עיניו, Et einav, we compare it with
Samson, ויאמר שמשון אותה קח לי כי היא ישרה בעיני, Vayomer Shimshon
ota kach li ki hi yashra be'einai, right? He wanted this woman.
וירא, Vayar, compare it with שכם Shechem that raped דינה, Dinah, וירא
אתה שכם בן חמור. Vayara ota Shechem ben Chamor. את כל ככר
הירדן, Et kol kikar hayarden, he saw the whole valley of the
Jordan. כי בעד אשה זונה עד ככר לחם, Ki be'ad isha zona
ad kikar lachem,
from Proverbs, comparing somebody going to a prostitute to somebody being so
destitute that they don't even have a piece of bread, and there's
other גמרא Gemara, places where sex and bread go together.
כי כלה משקה. Ki kulla mashke. יוסף Yosef story?
יוסף, Yosef, but the גמרא Gemara is talking about somebody who knows
he's
going to have relations... פת בסלו, pat besalo, right? They have bread.
פוטיפר Potiphar and לחם, lachem, and I think רש"י Rashi says that
means his wife
in the יוסף Yosef story.
I'm not seeing it here.
It's not in the גמרא, but it's in the לחם, lachem, לחם
lachem of פוטיפר. Potiphar.
Okay. כי כלה משקה, Ki kulla mashke, and then in הושע Hoshea
we say אלכה אחרי מאהבי נתני לחמי ומימי צמרי ופשתי שמני ושקויי.
elcha acharei me'ahavai notnei lachmi umeimai tzamri ufishti shamni veshikuyai. Okay. והא
מינס אניס? Veha mi-nes anis? Hey, but to your point, why are
you accusing him? Maybe he was an אנוס. anus. Isn't he also
like the victim of circumstances beyond his control? תנא משום רבי יוסי
בר רבי חוני,
Tana mishum Rabbi
Yosi bar Rabbi Choni, למה נקוד על ו' שבקומה של בכירה? lama
nakud al vav shebe-kuma shel bechirah?
What is the emphasis on the ו' vav
of
קומה? kuma? Like it says about לוט, Lot, ולא ידע בשכבה ובקומה,
velo yada beshichba uvekuma, okay. So he didn't
know—don't give it away, גמרא speaks for itself—לומר לך שבשכבה לא ידע
אבל בקומה ידע. lomar lecha shebeshichba lo yada aval bekuma yada. Maybe
he was drunk and he didn't know when they fell asleep or
fell into the act, right? He didn't know, but he knew when
she got up. And further, if that was really a mistake, what
happened on the second night? We can let the first thing go,
but we can't let the second thing go. מאי הוה ליה למיעבד?
Mai hava leh leme'vad? מה דהוה הוה. Mai de-hava hava. נפקא מינה
דלפניא אחרינא לא איבעי ליה למישתי. Nafka mina de-le-panya acharina lo iba'ei
leh le-mishtei. He should not have been drinking in the second night.
The fact that the first one happened,
happened, but the second one should not have happened.
Let's see if there's a better stopping point.
Okay, can I
just
close the לוט Lot thing?
Yeah. דרש רבא, Darash Rava, מאי דכתיב mai de-chtiv in משלי, Mishlei,
אח נפשע מקרית עז ומדינים כבריח ארמון.
ach nifsha mikiryat
oz umidyanim kevriach armon. Now we have a פסוק pasuk, from Proverbs:
a brother betrayed a strong city and their contentions are like the
bars of a castle. Okay. אח נפשע מקרית עז, Ach nifsha mikiryat
oz, the first part, the brother who betrayed, is לוט because he
removed himself from אברם. Avram. ומדינים כבריח ארמון,
Umidyanim kevriach
armon, שהטיל מדינים בין ישראל לעמון, she-hetil midyanim bein Yisrael le-Ammon, that
he put fights between ישראל Israel and the עמונים. Ammonites. And there's
a lot packed in this,
whatever, okay, forget it. We know also that מדין Midian is like
one of the heirs of לוט and we're told in דברים, Devarim,
לא יבא עמוני ומואבי בקהל ה', lo yavo Amoni uMoavi bikhal Hashem,
that an עמוני Amoni and a מואבי Moavi should not come in,
and yet, and yet, we know that King David's great-grandmother is רות
Ruth the מואביה. Moaviyah. So there's a whole discussion
that עמוני ומואבי Amoni uMoavi male should not come, but עמונית Amonit
and מואביה Moaviyah could come, and that in fact there's commentators that
say that דווקא davka because the daughters of לוט, who are really
relatives of אברם, Avram, right, the daughters of לוט had this... audacity
to do something so crazy, that those are qualities that we needed
in the kings of Israel. We couldn't have kings of Israel that
are just merciful and kind and this and this, they also needed
these qualities that they got from the Moabites first and then from
the Amonites. דרש רבא ואיתמר רב יצחק מאי דכתיב, Darash Rava ve'itmar
Rav Yitzchak mai dichtiv, and another פסוק, לתאוה יבקש נפרד בכל תושיה
יתגלה, leta'avah yivakesh nifrad bechol tushiyah yitgaleh, another משלי, Mishlei, he that
separates himself seeks his own desire and snares against all sound wisdom.
לתאוה יבקש נפרד זה לוט שנפרד
מאברהם ובכל תושיה יתגלה שנתגלה קלונו,
leta'avah yivakesh nifrad zeh Lot
shenifrad me'Avraham ubechol tushiyah yitgaleh shenitgaleh klono, so Lot is the one
that asked separation
and his name was revealed, everybody knew because Lot's daughter could have
said, oh you know, this should be a familiar story that we
hear in another religion nearby, we went into a cave, I don't
know what happened, I got pregnant and now I have a baby.
But she named the child מואב Moav that this is the seed
of the father. She was honest, proud of what she was doing,
and these qualities also went into the kings of Israel. And with
that,
a fabulous day, waiting for high schoolers to come next.
יישר כוח. Yashar koach. בוקר טוב. boker tov. בוקר טוב. boker tov.
מה שלומך? ma shlomecha?
מצוין. metzuyan. רגע אתה מוקלט. rega atah muklat.